Goldstein, Nathaniel Lawrence; Papers apap249
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Goldstein, Nathaniel Lawrence Papers
1922-1973
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap249
7.6 cubic ft.
This collection contains documents, materials, and memorabilia spanning the life and career of former New York Attorney General Nathaniel L. Goldstein, who served the state from 1943 to 1954. Goldstein, a Republican, is largely remembered for his work to delegitimize the Ku Klux Klan and contributions to the Albert Einstein College of Medicine (once part of Yeshiva University), as well as other facets of American security, philanthropy, and Jewish life in the mid-20th century. After his time in office, Goldstein continued his lifelong love of litigation by working in a private law firm.
Biographical / Historical
Nathaniel Lawerence Goldstein was born June 9, 1896 in Kings County, Brooklyn, New York City. In 1915 he received a Bachelor of Commercial Science from New York University and a Bachelor of Law in 1918 from New York Law School. He was a member of Alpha Epsilon Phi throughout, and after graduation served in the United States Army during World War I. He was awarded an honorary Doctor of Laws degree from Syracuse University in 1948, Hobart and William Smith Colleges in 1952, and New York Law School in 1957. Upon his return from the military, Goldstein worked as an accountant and eventually began to practice law with Brooklyn Assemblyman Charles C. Lockwood.
Goldstein was admitted to the New York Bar in 1918. He became a C.P.A. in 1919. From 1940-1942, he was the assistant chief counsel to the Director of Selective Service in New York. Goldstein was a delegate to the Republican National Convention in 1940, 1944, and 1948 and the people of New York elected him as their state Attorney General in 1942, 1946, and 1950. Goldstein spent much of his time as attorney general dealing with rent-control litigation, the drugs epidemic, and financial crime. Goldstein also aimed to withdraw the New York State charter for the Ku Klux Klan, and was able to give the FBI 1,100 names of members of the Ku Klux Klan and the Hitler-resurgent German American Bund. Following his retirement in 1954 from the Attorney General's office, he became a member of the law firm of Goldstein, Judd, and Gurfein.
Goldstein had many and varied organizational interests and was active in the Jewish community of New York City. He was a member of the United Palestine Appeal. He also served as a director and vice-president of the Wilkie Memorial of Freedom House, a trustee of the New York Law School, and chairman emeritus of the Board of Overseers of Albert Einstein College of Medicine of Yeshiva University, proving his sincere interest in higher education. He was a member of the American Bar Association, Zionist Organization of America, American Legion, Freemasons, B'nai B'rith, and Elks and acted as special counsel for the law firm Finley, Kumble, Wagner, Heine, and Underbreg. Among his other activities he was the Associate Chairmanship of the United Jewish Appeal, held membership in the United States delegation to the United Nation's Narcotic Drug Control Commission, and past post commander in the American Legion. He also contributed many articles to various legal publications.
Goldstein died in Manhattan in 1981 and was survived by his wife Etta May Brown and his children Lois Lowenstein and Steven Goldstein.
Scope and Contents
The Nathaniel L. Goldstein Papers contain filed materials which document Goldstein's life and career. This includes correspondence, photographs, speeches, small publications, even birthday and greeting cards. The scrapbooks comprise a signficant portion of the collection. There are over 27 in total, but only half are stable enough for researchers to view. These scrapbooks do not hold photographs but rather a litany of newspaper clippings and typed documents, mostly speeches, by or about Goldstein and relating to his career. The paper backing of most of these scrapbooks is of poor quality and now fragile, the newsprint has become brittle with time, and the adhesives (glue, tape) used to hold the papers and clippings in place have failed. The scrapbooks have been unbound and placed individually in oversized boxes. All scrapbooks are very dusty, and researchers are advised to wear a face mask when handling them.
Please note that while there may be speeches or newspaper clippings in the scrapbooks that refer to Goldstein's efforts to combat the Ku Klux Klan and the German American Bund, there is no correspondence, reports or other foldered materials documenting this work in the collection.
Arrangement
The Nathaniel L. Goldstein Papers are arranged alphabetically. There are no series.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Nathaniel Lawrence Goldstein donated his papers to Syracuse University in 1963-1964. Additonal materials were donated in 1968-1969 and 1971-1973. In 2006, materials were transferred to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collecctions and Archives.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted with the exception of a select number of scrapbooks. These scrapbooks are physically unstable and cannot be currently handled by patrons.
Goldstein, Nathaniel L., 1896-1981; Politicians--New York (State); Politics and Politicians; Practice of law--New York (State); Charities--New York (State)
- "Acceptance Speech by Former New York Attorney General Goldstein," Congressional Record-Proceedings and Debates of the 89th Congress, First Session, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Albert Einstein College of Medicine Materials (Folders 1 of 3), 1953-1973; Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Albert Einstein College of Medicine Materials (Folders 2 of 3), 1953-1973; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Albert Einstein College of Medicine Materials (Folders 3 of 3), 1953-1973; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Albert Einstein College of Medicine Materials, 1969; 1971 (Flat-file 1)
- Albert Einstein College of Medicine Tenth Annual Founders Dinner Scrapbook, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "Allocation of Income for Purposes of Corporate Taxation," Taxes: The Tax Magazine; Tax Law Review; reprint, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Announcements, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "The Anteroom of History," The Churchman, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Attorney General Heads Huge Public Law Business," The Empire Statesman, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Awards and Citations, 1947-1960; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Bulletin on Narcotics - Vol IV, No. 2, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Cards (All Occasions), 1955-1956; 1963; Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Career Correspondence, 1922-1968; Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- "The Case of Palestine," Palestine - The Jewish National Home, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- "The Cemetery: A Public Problem"; "Cemetery Law"; "Cemetery Law: A Guide to the 1949 Revision"; "Report of the Attorney General on the Subject of Cemeteries", Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Club, Association, and Greek Life Materials, 1965; 1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- "Condemnation Procedure in State of New York," New York State Bar Association Bulletin, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Economic Conference 1968 Delegate Card (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Election Law Guide for Special Deputy Attorneys - General, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Extra Clippings from Scrapbook #8 - "Press Clippings - A Few of the Highlights", 1945-1947; 1951; Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Extra Clippings from Scrapbook #10 - Scrapbooked Documents, 1947; Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Extra Clippings from Scrapbook #15 - Untitled, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Family Materials, 1950-1957; 1960-1963; 1972 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- The First, Second, Third Report of the New York State Crime Commission to the Governor, the Attorney General, and the Legislature of the State of New York, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- "Fixing of Agents' Commissions in Combination by Insurance Companies Held Illegal," New York State Bar Association Bulletin, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- "The Generals Stayed Away!" The ADL Bulletin, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- "Goldstein Acts to End Klan," The Empire Statesman, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- "Goldstein Rules on Veterans' Preference," The State Employee, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- The Harry S. Truman Center for the Advancement of Peace in Jerusalem, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- "If I Were Nat Goldstein", 1950 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- "Interstate Enforcement of the Tax Laws of Sister States," State Government; Taxes: The Tax Magazine, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Invitations and RSVPs, 1954; 1958-1960; 1963-1965; Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
- "Judicial Encroachment on State's Rights," New York State Bar Association Bulletin, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- "Judicial Review of Administrative Action Through Article 78 of the Civil Practice Act (1937-1951)," Syracuse Law Review (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Law of Condemnation - The Post-War Program of Public Improvement in New York State, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Manuscript and Publication of "Security for the Professions: A Plan for More Equitable Tax Treatment", 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Manuscripts for Speeches, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Manuscripts for Speeches, 1946-1956 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Manuscripts for Speeches, 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Manuscripts for Speeches, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Manuscript of "Compulsory Cures for Drug Addicts?", 1953 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Manuscript of "Report by Attorney General on Ownership of Stock in Small Drug Companies", 1952 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Manuscript of "That 'Most Remarkable Work' - The Constitution of the United States", Undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Manuscript of "The Office of the Attorney General of the State of New York", 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Manuscript of the Review of "The Strange Case of Alger Hiss", 1953 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- "March Toward Home Rule,"National Municipal Review; Association of Towns Digest of 1945 Laws Affecting Towns and Counties; reprint, Undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Menus and Guest List from Nathaniel Goldstein' s Birthday Party, 1951; 1953-1954; Undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Mount Scopus/Hebrew University Materials (Folder 1 of 2), 1964; 1967-1969; 1971-1972; Undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Mount Scopus/Hebrew University Materials (Folder 2 of 2), 1964; 1967-1969; 1971-1972; Undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Narcotics, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Narcotics 1952 - A Further Study of Problems and Plans, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Narcotics - A Growing Problem… A Public Challenge… A Plan for Action…, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- "New York and the War Veteran," Veteran News, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- New York Law School Bulletin, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- New York Law School Commencement Programs, 1956-1957; 1959; 1961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- "New York Proves It: Laws Can Cut Discrimination," The Christian Unitarian Register, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- New York State Narcotics Investigation - Testimony Given Before Attorney General Goldstein 1951-1952 Volume 1 (Oversize 1)
- New York State Narcotics Investigation - Testimony Given Before Attorney General Goldstein 1951-1952 Volume 2, Undated (Oversize 2)
- New York State Narcotics Investigation - Testimony Given Before Attorney General Goldstein 1951-1952 Volume 3, Undated (Oversize 2)
- Newspaper Clippings About Nathaniel Goldstein, 1943-1967; Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Newspaper Clippings By/About Nathaniel Goldstein, 1966-1967; 1970; 1972; Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- "The Office of the Attorney General of the State," New York State Bar Association Bulletin, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- "Our Forest Preserve," The New York State Conservationist, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Outgoing Correspondence, 1954-1961 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Personal Correspondence (A-D), 1949; 1952-1962; 1965-1966; 1968; 1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Personal Correspondence (E-L), 1942; 1952-1963; 1965-1967; 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Personal Correspondence (M-R), 1951-1952; 1954-1962; 1968; 1972 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Personal Correspondence (S-Y), 1942; 1951-1957; 1959-1962; 1966 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Photographs from Various Events, 1943-1967; Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- "Post-War Planning in New York," State Government, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Press Release About Nathaniel Goldstein, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- "Private Charitable Foundations After Tax Reform," American Bar Association Journal, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Presentments by Grand Jury - Legislative Investigation, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- "Report of State Attorney General on M.D. Stockholders in Drug Firms," New York Medicine, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Scrapbook #1 - "'50-'51", 1950-1951; Undated (Volume 1)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Currently unavailable to be reviewed because of present physical condition.
- Scrapbook #2 - "1951", Undated (Volume 2)
- Scrapbook #3 - "Election Releases", 1948-1950 (Volume 3)
- Scrapbook #4 - "Feb 1954", 1951; 1953-1954 (Volume 4)
- Scrapbook #5 - "Narcotics: March 1951 - July 17, 1951", Undated (Volume 5)
- Scrapbook #6 - "Narcotics: Volume II - June 1951-September 15, 1951" (Volume 6)
- Scrapbook #7 - "Narcotics: Volume III - September 15, 1951 to December 31, 1951" (Volume 7)
- Scrapbook #8 - "Press Clippings - A Few of the Highlights", 1942-1948; Undated (Volume 8)
- Scrapbook #9 - "Releases - January - April 1948" (Volume 9)
- Scrapbook #10 - Scrapbooked Documents, 1943-1949; Undated (Volume 10)
- Scrapbook #11 - Scrapbooked Documents, 1949-1954; Undated (Volume 11)
- Scrapbook #12 - Scrapbooked Documents, 1953 (Volume 12)
- Scrapbook #13 - Untitled, 1943-1947 (Volume 13)
- Scrapbook #14 - Untitled, 1948; Undated (Volume 14)
- Scrapbook #15 - Untitled, 1948-1949 (Volume 15)
- Scrapbook #16 - Untitled, 1948-1951; Undated (Volume 16)
- Scrapbook #17 - Untitled, 1949-1950 (Volume 17)
- Scrapbook #18 - Untitled, 1949-1950 (Volume 18)
- Scrapbook #19 - Untitled, 1949-1950; Undated (Volume 19)
- Scrapbook #20 - Untitled, 1949-1950; Undated (Volume 20)
- Scrapbook #21 - Untitled, 1950-1951 (Volume 21)
- Scrapbook #22 - Untitled, 1950-1951; Undated (Volume 22)
- Scrapbook #23 - Untitled, 1951-1952 (Volume 23)
- Scrapbook #24 - Untitled, 1951-1952; Undated (Volume 24)
- Scrapbook #25 - Untitled, 1952-1953 (Volume 25)
- Scrapbook #26 - Untitled, 1952-1953; Undated (Volume 26)
- Scrapbook #27 - Untitled, 1953-1954; Undated (Volume 27)
- Speeches, 1966; 1972 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- State of Israel Bond Materials, 1972; Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- State of New York Annual Report of Nathaniel L. Goldstein Attorney General to The Senate and Assembly for 1948, Undated (Flat-file 2)
- State of New York - Informal Opinions Relating to Municipal Government, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- State of New York - Informal Opinions Relating to Municipal Government, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- "The Strange Case of Alger Hiss," Northwestern University Law Review, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- "Suckers Are Made, Not Born," The Exchange (Box 3, Folder 12)
- "'That Most Remarkable Work,' The Constitution of the United States," Law Review Digest; Notre Dame Lawyer; reprint, 1953; Undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
- "To the Maker of the Peace," The New Palestine, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Transcript of the Lectures Given by the Selective Service Administration in Conjunction with the New York County Lawyers Association, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- True Detective, "Stocketeer Buster", 1946 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- The Unconstitutionality of a Federal Tax Upon State and Municipal Bond Interest, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Various Event Programs, 1945-1948; 1951-1952; 1955; 1960 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- "Watch Out for the Cancer Frauds", 1951 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- "We Can Cure Drug Addicts," The American Legion Magazine, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- "The Year 1950 in the Attorney General's Office," New York State Bar Bulletin, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 7)